We don't need inflation. All these
stories that the economists tell to try
to justify deliberately creating
inflation are it's all wrong. The
government has brainwashed people into
believing that inflation is a good thing
because the government benefits from it.
The government steals through inflation.
Inflation is really like a hidden tax
and they should be raising rates.
They're cutting rates. We're pursuing a
very inflationary monetary policy
because we have so much debt. They're
trying to bring down mortgage rates.
They're trying to bring down long-term
bond rates. They need to create
inflation to do that. debase the value
of the dollar. Foreign central banks can
see this. They're getting rid of their
dollars. What are they replacing their
dollars with? They're replacing it with
gold. They're moving away from US
dollars and US treasuries to gold. It's
the debate with CZ.
People confuse store value with price.
The price is not value. Price is what
you pay, right? Value is what you get.
I mean Bitcoin is nothing. Has nothing
in common with a physical valuable
precious metal. What they say is that
inflation is necessary to have a
prosperous economy. We have to make sure
prices go up. If prices went down,
nobody would buy anything, which is
because
the real way that inflation benefits the
rich is it wipes out Inflation benefits
debtors and hurts creditors. My
investment portfolio reflects what I
expect the government to do, not what
they should do. But
Inflation is good for the top 0.1%
though because you own asset. Why are
you even fighting the system? You called
out the '08 financial crisis. Are we
seeing the same thing now? We're in a
bigger bubble.
[Music]
I am with Peter Schiff right now and I
am so excited because you're one of the
most requested guest. People love you.
Just just read the comment section.
People are talking about your style,
your insights, also your skin and
everything. Uh well, thanks. Well, my
skin is not looking that great today. I
had I had like a I kind of broke out
somehow. I don't know what I what
happened. It's the debate with CZ later.
>> No, it was from before that. It's from
Can we talk about the debate a little
bit cuz it is going to be in a couple
hours and I am intrigued. Why is the
topic tokenized gold versus Bitcoin
instead of gold versus Bitcoin? Well,
it's the origin of how this came about
and I think it's more of a conversation.
Obviously a bit adversarial but not like
a formal debate. There's no moderator.
It's just kind of the two of us uh
having having a discussion about about
it. But the the way it it it it evolved
So I was
doing an interview on another popular
crypto uh podcast and the topic of
tokenized gold came up. Mhm. And and so
I said, "Yeah, you know, I I I certainly
think that that's a viable use of
blockchain." Uh ironically, it's
probably one of the few things that
could actually come out of it would be
uh a a way of making gold uh an even
better medium of exchange through the
tokenization, making gold more portable,
more fungible, you know, easier to use
uh you know, in commerce. So I said,
"Look, you know, I'm probably going to
have my own I I started something called
T Gold." Uh and right now it's just a
page on the SchiffGold website, but if
you go to tgold.com, it'll take you
there where you can set up an account.
And this is to have uh gold where it we
don't deliver it like SchiffGold. People
buy gold and we we send out the bars or
the coins. We mail it to their address.
But with T Gold, you just buy whatever,
you know, $100, $1,000, you know, $5,000
worth of gold or silver. And we don't
deliver it. You buy it and it's, you
know, segregated but it's it we vault
vaulted and have it, you know, stored
for you. So you just have, you know,
whatever quantity you want.
Ultimately, what I'm working on is in
addition to being able to withdraw
your gold physically, you'll be able to
withdraw it in the form of a token. Mhm.
And that token basically just represents
your ownership of that gold.
But once you have it in the form of a
token, you know, you can transfer it to
somebody else. Now they would own the
gold instead of you. And you don't have
to transfer all of your gold, whatever
fraction you want because it's all
divisible into, you know, tiny
increments just like, you know, Bitcoin
would be.
Um so I I mentioned I'm developing this
and and you know, also I'm going to have
it so, you know, people can get a debit
card, credit card tied to their gold
account. And you know, so they could
turn their gold into a fiat currency,
you know, at point of sale. So if they
you know, wanted to go to a restaurant
and you know, they didn't have any cash
and they you know, they could use their
gold, right? They could just use the
card and gold would be sold to cover the
the cost of the the meal or whatever
they're spending their money on. So I
wanted to just build, you know, this
ecosystem where it was easy for people
to use their gold
as money, not just as a store value
where they're keeping gold, you know, in
a safe or, you know, in a shoe box, you
know, hidden in their closet. But where
they're carrying their gold around on on
their smartphone or on, you know, on a
debit card where, you know, they could
use it. All right. So CZ saw the
interview
and commented that uh this is, you know,
this isn't going to work cuz it's like a
trust me, bro kind of
um concept cuz he said you have to trust
the third party with your gold. So it's
not going to work, right? Cuz Bitcoin is
trustless. You don't have to trust any
third parties.
Uh you just, you know,
own your Bitcoin.
And so when he said this
I mean, initially my initial reaction
was who's he kidding because he you
know, it's Binance.
Binance is a third party. You put your
Bitcoin on a Binance platform, you're
trusting Binance. Right? So people trust
him all the time
uh with their crypto. So how is that
different than trusting, you know, a you
know,
company uh like a Brinks for example to
hold your gold. They've been doing it
for 160 years and nobody's lost any gold
uh with Brinks. So you can trust third
parties. But also I know that
one of the biggest things in crypto
right now
is uh stablecoins.
And what's a stablecoin? Well, that's
where you have a third party who you
trust with your dollars or, you know,
your euros or your yen, whatever, you
know, your token is is stabilized to.
Most of them are dollar tokens, right?
Like Tether. You're you're trusting
Tether, you know, when you when you buy
Tether's token, you've trusted a third
party that they have the dollars to back
up your your token.
So if he's going to say that, well,
tokenized gold is no good, well, then
then neither are,
you know, you know, the stablecoins. The
whole He's He's basically throwing the
whole industry under the bus at the same
time he's, you know, he's criticizing
tokenized gold. So
I I pointed that out. I said, "Look, you
know, I'm happy to debate this with
you." Like I you know, I love to debate
tokenized gold versus Bitcoin, not just
regular gold
>> Right. because it was the concept of
tokenized gold that he was Yeah.
>> you know, he was critical of but said I
had it wrong.
And so he said, "Yeah, let's do a
debate." I'm like, "Great." And I'm
trying to figure out when, you know, all
of a sudden like everybody wants to host
it. All these podcasters, big
podcasters, we want to host the debate.
We want to do the debate. Everybody
wants to do the the the the CZ-Schiff
debate. And then CZ ends up saying,
"Hey, why don't you why don't we have
the debate in in Dubai at my you know,
Blockchain Week is coming up." Which is
not what I had in mind when I threw it
out there. I was going to just do
something from my home, you know, uh on
the internet like, you know, some of the
other like, you know, crypto, you know,
debates I've had.
Uh but since he extended the invitation
and was gracious enough to, you know,
accept the debate uh I wasn't going to,
you know, refuse it. Mhm. So I came out
here. Nice. And you know,
>> And you posted a lot of selfies again.
In every Bitcoin conferences, crypto
conferences, I see your face everywhere.
People love you.
>> Again, a lot of the people that are
hardcore enough to come to a conference,
right? Cuz I mean, if you just casually
buy a little Bitcoin, you know, you're
not necessarily going to go to a Bitcoin
conference. But the people that go to
the conferences are are more into it.
Before you get into Bitcoin, usually you
have to have a a certain perspective
>> Right.
>> on things. Mhm. And a lot of people that
have those perspectives where they
distrust government, distrust central
banks
um fiat currency and all that
a lot of the people who feel that way
feel that way because of me. Mhm. Right?
I'm the one that, you know,
got them thinking that way. I put them
on a path and they went down the path
and eventually took a detour and got to
Bitcoin.
But, you know, had I not put them on
that path, they wouldn't have found the
detour to Bitcoin. And and then even
people that necessarily didn't buy
Bitcoin because of me
but who own Bitcoin and know about me
um I say a lot of the things
that
lead people to want to buy Bitcoin.
Right. Even though I tell them not to.
But a lot of the things that I say, for
example, as to, you know, why you would
want to own gold, they'll just apply
that to Bitcoin. Yes, I agree.
Everything Peter says and I'm buying
Bitcoin because I believe in what he's
saying. Some of the characteristics are
the same. No, I don't think there are
any
characteristics.
>> None? No, because I mean, Bitcoin is
nothing. Has nothing in common with a
physical
metal, a valuable precious metal.
The The only thing that
Bitcoin has in common with gold
is if you look at gold's monetary
properties, apart from the fact that
it's a store of value, which Bitcoin
can't copy at all because there's no
value there to store. People used salt
as money. That's where the word salary
comes from, but cattle has been money. I
mean, you know, there's a lot of weird
commodities that that have been money.
But what makes gold
better money
is its portability, its durability, its
divisibility, its fungibility.
Bitcoin has those characteristics. It is
fungible, it is divisible, it is
portable. It is durable, right? So, it's
it it it has those things.
But
when you separate that from the
intrinsic value of the metal, right?
What, you know, the the, you know, what
you can do with gold that you can't do
with other metals or other other
elements, right? When you when you when
you separate that
the portability and divisibility are
meaningless.
Because when you're dividing gold,
you're dividing something. When you're
porting gold, you're you're porting
something.
But when you divide Bitcoin, you're
dividing nothing. You're porting
nothing. You know, there there's there's
nothing there. So, the only the only
thing that gives Bitcoin its market
price and cuz it it has a price, right?
Bitcoin, you know, Bitcoins are not over
$90,000, right? They're The reason
that somebody is willing to pay $90,000
for a Bitcoin or 93,000 is because he
thinks that in the future somebody's
going to pay more.
But isn't that every financial product?
>> No.
I mean
yes, when you buy a stock, the idea is
that
the price will go up. But it's supposed
to be a function of the business having
more value. So, I I I invest in a
company.
And I think that in the future that
company is going to have more earnings
than it has today, right? It's going to
grow its earnings.
Maybe it's going to pay a higher
dividend that it pays now, or maybe
it'll pay a dividend. Maybe it doesn't
even pay a dividend now, but I believe
in the future it will when it's more
mature company and earns more money. So,
I'm betting on
the growth of the business, you know, on
business. But Bitcoin doesn't grow, it
doesn't do anything. It stays exactly
the same. I mean,
the Bitcoin is just nothing's going to
change other than the price.
But why would the price of Bitcoin go up
if the Bitcoin itself is not going to
change? It's not going to generate any
more income cuz it generates no income,
right?
And it's a function of expecting people
just to pay more for the exact same
thing. Right? If I think someone's going
to pay more for my stock in the future,
it's because the company is earning more
money, right? It's a It's a more
valuable business cuz it's
has more sales, it has more income.
And so, that's changing, but Bitcoin is
never going to change. The only thing
that can change is the price.
And the only reason the price is going
to be higher is if somebody is willing
to pay that higher price. Or money in
the world becomes more. People keep on
printing and that is just a system.
Right. Well, look, if if
we create inflation, right? Then prices
go up for things.
But they may not go up for Bitcoin
because prices go up for things that we
need and have to buy, right? So, if I
have to buy, you know, gas
and the government doubles the money
supply all right, well, maybe I have to
pay twice as much for the gas that I
need.
But I don't need Bitcoin for anything.
So, it's not a function of, you know,
how much money there is. The function is
the demand for Bitcoin.
You know, and what drives the demand for
Bitcoin? It's the belief that the price
is going to go up. That's That's all
That's all of where it comes from.
And And so you need to have more people
that believe the price is going to go
up.
And And And when the price does go up,
people have to think, "Okay, it's going
to go up some more." Right? It has to
always go up. Because that's the only
way to drive the buying because every
buyer has to believe that there's
another buyer who's going to pay more
than they did, right? That's the whole
greater fool uh concept that drives
Bitcoin. But the reason that the greater
fool uh concept doesn't work is because
you eventually run out of fools. There
is no greatest fool, all right? You have
the last one and then everything
collapses. But the problem is
you don't know where you are. You don't
know if there's another fool that's
going to follow you or if you're, you
know, you're the one stuck holding the
bag.
But I think a lot of the people in the
Bitcoin community
who never sell their Bitcoin, right? Cuz
they've been brainwashed by the people
who do sell their Bitcoin, right? That
That's who made up this never sell your
Bitcoin. It's the people who want to
sell theirs that want everybody else not
to, right? Because they have to maintain
the market and they don't want every
They want to compete with other people.
So, the people who just hold hold,
right?
Uh they're all really going to lose
everything cuz they're going to hold
They're holding nothing.
The The only way you're going to make
money in Bitcoin is to sell.
But
you only make money because somebody
else bought.
And so, the the the the profits that are
ultimately made in Bitcoin
just represents the money that other
people lost in Bitcoin, right? There's
no There's no net wealth, right? When
you when when miners create Bitcoin or
they solve a mathematical problem
uh to produce a Bitcoin
they haven't increased the wealth of the
world. They haven't They haven't added
anything of real value. They These
aren't factories that are producing
goods, right? That make my life better.
They're just They're just solving
meaningless math problems and they're
just creating these tokens, right? So,
the world is not richer because we have
all this Bitcoin.
Uh but what what Bitcoin does is enables
a transfer of wealth. Right.
>> The people who sell Bitcoin make money.
The people who buy Bitcoin lose money.
Now, if the people who buy Bitcoin can
then turn around and sell Bitcoin at a
higher price, then they will make money.
But just because the person who paid the
higher price, now he loses the money. I
have a question. How is that different
than gold? Our producer there, he used
to be a Bitcoiner, now he loves gold,
too.
And I mean, this is I love Bitcoin and I
talk about Bitcoin all day, but the
world is huge. People have different
views. And
for people that buys gold, not everyone
wants to wear jewelry or they don't use
it in electronics, but for the same
reason why people buy Bitcoin. Well
I agree that there are investors who buy
Bitcoin for the same reason that I buy
gold. Right.
But I think they're misguided to do that
and I think eventually
that's going to stop because
>> can talk about why is gold valuable
rather instead of like I mean, gold is
value. Look, see, I I'm I'm wearing a
gold watch, right? And so
if this watch was not made of gold,
Rolex couldn't sell it for anywhere near
as much money. I mean, I guess they
could have made it out of uh
uh steel,
right? Uh you know,
and they make watches that are not made
out of gold. I mean, you could still
have a watch, but it's not
going to be as nice,
right? It's
It's not going to I mean, um you know,
so
gold lends itself because of its
properties, right? I mean, I can go You
know, you can swim with a gold watch,
you can take a shower with it, it's not
going to rust, right? It's not going to
tarnish.
Um you know, uh it it And so, this watch
is going to look exactly like this, you
know, 10 years from now, 20 years from
now. I can, you know, my my son, my
grandson could wear this watch and it'll
look just as nice, right? And say, "Hey,
this is my great-grandfather's watch.
It's been passed down, right? It's an
heirloom."
But what what gives gold its value are
the properties
that it has that are unique to gold.
And there is a lot of demand for gold in
industry
not just in jewelry.
But there are a lot of industrial
applications
where gold is used, even though it's
very expensive.
It's used because nothing else can do
what it does.
Now, in some cases, I mean, wires, you
know, wiring is not made out of gold,
it's made out of copper.
It might It It would probably better if
it was made out of gold, but it's too
expensive. So, it it in in a lot of
applications, you can substitute
copper for gold because it'll work,
right? But in those applications where
you can't, like I I can't make my watch
out of copper. But in the applications
where you need to have gold, then you
buy gold. And And And And so there's
real demand for gold. That's what gives
it its value. What makes it money are
the other characteristics, like
durability, portability, fungibility,
but its inherent value comes from the
fact that it's a precious metal uh that
has, you know, all these unique and
valuable properties.
The reason the price is high is because
it's also scarce. So, gold
can do a lot of great things, but we
don't have a lot of it. Mhm. Right? If
there was more of it around the earth,
the price wouldn't be as high because,
you know, it'd be more readily
available. So, it's very valuable and
very scarce, and so it has a a high
price, which
you know, also lends itself to being
money. But, even if you are not a
jeweler and even if you are not, you
know, making uh computers or in
aerospace or in medicine or any of the
places where gold
when you're buying it,
you're buying it because other people
uh
use gold, even if you don't. Like
in in prisons, right? Cigarettes
become money, right? Why are those
cigarettes valuable? They're valuable
because smokers want them cuz they
smoke. Now, you may not smoke. You could
be in prison and and you don't smoke.
But, you know there's somebody that
does. And the fact that there are some
smokers in prison, that's why cigarettes
have value. So, even if you don't smoke,
the fact that there's somebody that
smokes. Now, if there's no smokers at
all, then the cigarettes have no value.
They're not going to be money if nobody
can smoke them. There needs to be an
actual user
that preserves the underlying value of
the cigarette, right? And and so, the
same with gold. When you own gold, even
if you don't use it, somebody else will
use it. Somebody else does need it,
whether it's today or 100 years in the
future,
right? Someone's going to use that gold.
So, that's what gives it its value. But,
with Bitcoin,
nobody uses it for anything,
right? Other than trading, right? Which
doesn't count. Bitcoin can't be a store
of value. People say, "Oh, Bitcoin's a
store of value." No, there's no value
that you can store.
And, you know, gold is a store of value
because gold uh doesn't decay, it
doesn't, you know, decompose or, you
know, so I can make if I have a bar of
gold, that could be melted down in a
thousand years and made into jewelry or
made, you know, made in in used in all
kinds of applications. But, that's not
the case with Bitcoin. It can't be used
for anything today and it can't be used
for anything tomorrow.
But, people confuse store value with
price. People say, "Well, it's a great
store of value because I bought it 10
years ago and it's, you know, it's 10
times higher." Yeah, that's not a store
of value. You bought it and the price
went up,
right? But, price
is not the same as value, right?
Something can be overpriced or
underpriced, right? Price is not value.
Price is what you pay, right? Value is
what you get.
Uh and price can be very divorced
divorced from value, right? It depends
on on on the circumstances. But, you
can't store price, right? So, just
because Bitcoin the price is 93,000 for
a Bitcoin, I can't store that.
Because price is a function of supply
and demand.
And it's possible that in the future
there's no demand for Bitcoin, which
means the price is zero if nobody wants
it,
right? There's never going to be a
situation where there's no demand for
gold. In fact, the lower the price of
gold, the more demand there is.
Bitcoin works the the reverse. People
want Bitcoin when the price is going up
cuz they think it'll keep going up. When
the price starts to crash, people don't
want to buy. Well, the past 2 years uh
gold price has gone up a lot and a lot
of governments are buying gold now, but
the utility of gold didn't go up that
much. So, it is a store of value in some
ways. People are afraid of either
uh currency inflation, all that. What is
it that you're seeing? No, it it is a
store of value and and people are afraid
of inflation.
>> Right. Not
not as as as fearful as they should be.
I mean, I think you're going to have a
lot more buying,
but I think the central bank buying
is more about the US dollar
and the, you know, credibility of the
United States to ever get its fiscal
house in order.
Uh we have deficits that are
skyrocketing out of control. You've been
talking about that since '06. Yes, well,
it's been a problem. I've been was
talking about before that. I mean, this
this problem did not
happen overnight. It's been building
over the decades. But, it's getting
worse, isn't that what you're
>> And everybody keeps saying it's not a
problem because, you know, it's for the
long term, right? Well, it is a problem.
You know, it's been a problem and now
it's a much bigger problem, but the
central banks
uh understand this.
They see that, you know, our interest on
our debt is, you know, 1.2, 1.3 trillion
a year. It's growing exponentially.
The budget deficits are two, three
trillion a year and that's when we're
not in recession.
So, the next official recession, we'll
probably have a four trillion dollar
deficit that year, maybe more.
Uh
you know, the Fed is, you know, already
stopped shrinking the balance sheet. I
think it's very close to going back to
quantitative easing. They're already
cutting rates when rates are too low and
they should be raising rates, they're
cutting rates.
So, we're we're we're, you know,
pursuing a very inflationary monetary
policy because we have so much debt. Uh
they're trying to bring down mortgage
rates, they're trying to bring down
long-term bond rates. They need to
create inflation to do that.
So, they debase the value of the dollar
and foreign central banks can see this
and they're getting rid of their
dollars. And what are they replacing
their dollars with? They're replacing it
with gold. I mean, that is the most
viable substitute for the dollar,
it's gold. And, you know, a lot of
people who have taken the dollar's role
as a reserve currency for granted, you
know, they've done that because they
didn't see a viable replacement. They
said, "Well, you know, the euro's not
going to be the reserve currency or the
yen or the, you know, RMB."
But, they overlooked gold,
right? Uh gold, you know, it's not,
you know, in that hamper. They keep
saying the the the dollar is the
cleanest dirty shirt in the hamper,
right? Well, maybe so. I don't I
disagree with that, but even if you
accept that premise,
gold is not in that hamper. Gold is
pristine, right? It's not dirty at all.
And that's where the central banks are
moving. They're moving away from US
dollars and US Treasuries to gold. And
there are political reasons they're
doing that, too. It's not just purely
economic. But, that is how the pendulum
is swinging.
And to the extent that central banks are
going to hold a lot more gold in the
future than they do now, you know,
without a big increase in the supply of
gold, right? The price of gold has to go
up for that reason. Um but, as
uh individuals
um and
institutions
start to realize that they also need to
have exposure to gold,
>> Mhm. that's going to increase the demand
for gold. They haven't realized it yet?
>> No, I mean, maybe a small number. Right.
>> Right? Like my clients, you know, have
realized it. You know, some with my
help, some figured it out on their own,
right? And just sought me out as a place
to buy gold. I didn't have to convince
them to buy it, they already decided.
They just bought it from me because I
got I gave them a good price.
>> Mhm. Or they trusted me, right? Uh but,
a lot of people own gold because I
convinced them that they should buy it,
right? And then and then they bought it
from me.
Um
but, um the price is going to go up as
more investors want to buy
a relatively scarce commodity,
you know, there's not a lot of
production coming online for gold. It's
not like anybody's discovered a huge new
gold mine.
Uh I think some of the the new supply
for investors may come from jewelry that
gets melted down. I mean, some people
uh let's say in the US, if they lose
their job and the economy is, you know,
very difficult and they need money and
they have some old jewelry that they
don't wear, they may just sell it. And,
you know, companies will buy it for the
value of the gold. So, but that's not
going to move the needle really on
supply. There's not going to be, you
know, that might really happen with
silver, too, right? People start
bringing in their silverware, right?
Silver gets up to $100.
Is it really what you're saying now? Oh,
yeah. I mean, well, I I don't I don't
think people are melting down their
silverware yet. Silver's almost $60.
>> Right. But, I mean, I think that that's
going to be,
you know, a source of supply. It's going
to happen cuz people are going to be in
desperate situation where they have a
hard time paying the bills.
They might say, "You know, I got some
silverware,
you know, our good silverware that we
don't really use very often, but if I
can sell my silverware for $30,000, you
know, that's might come in handy." You
know, where that silverware, you know,
might have only been worth $5,000,
you know,
you know, now it's like $30,000. Well,
at that price, I'd rather have the cash
than the good the good silver, you know.
My curiosity
wants me to ask you one question.
Inflation is good for the top 0.1%
though because you own asset, you want
governments to print. Why are you even
fighting this system? It's good it works
in your favor.
Well, um
you know,
I I would agree that
the way my portfolio is positioned,
the the the the more mistakes the
government makes, the more they screw up
the economy, the more inflation they
create, the wealthier I'm going to be.
>> Right.
Right, but I've invested
based on
what I think the government's going to
do,
right? Mhm.
>> Not on what the government should do,
but what I believe it will do. Okay.
>> Now, just because I've invested
based on the premise that the
government's going to do everything
wrong,
I'm not going to advocate that the
government do everything wrong.
I'm going to advocate that they do the
right thing.
And if they do the right thing, then my
investments are going to be harmed.
It's because I don't expect them to be
to to listen to me.
But I would rather I would rather the
government do the right thing and then I
would invest based on them doing the
right thing.
>> Because I think I can make a lot more
money if the government does the right
thing cuz I know how I I would know how
to invest. First of all, I would be
short a lot of stuff right now. If I
knew the government was going to do the
right thing, I would be shorting a lot
of things because prices need to come
down.
>> Right. Right, doing the right thing
means stock prices go down, real estate
prices go down and so I would be short a
lot of the stuff. So, my investment
portfolio reflects what I expect the
government to do, not what they should
do. But I never advocate just because
I'm going to profit from inflation,
right? I'm not advocating that the
government create inflation. I think
that's wrong. Right? And I think
everybody would be better off. It's not
like the rich
benefit from inflation.
I think the rich would benefit from a a
a stronger economy where the you know,
we we had sound money. I think the rich
could get even richer. If I borrowed,
you know, $100 million
to buy,
you know,
$200 million
worth of assets, right? Whether it's
real estate or stocks and now the
government creates a lot of inflation,
right?
The value of my debt goes down, right?
The the real value of my assets hasn't
really changed. The government doubles
the money supply all else being equal,
prices double, my real estate double, my
stocks double, but my cost of living
doubles, right? So, I'm not any
wealthier. But where I've made money is
the value of my debt has been cut in
half. I used to owe $100 million and now
I effectively owe $50 million. So, the
real way that inflation benefits the
rich is it wipes out their debt. Mhm.
Now,
inflation also reduces the debt
for people who have credit card debt or
you know, but they don't have an asset
on the other side of that, right? They
didn't they didn't borrow money to buy
an asset. They bought borrowed money to
buy food, right? To take a vacation. So,
all of that stuff is gone. So, they
don't really they don't benefit cuz they
don't have the the asset that's going
up. They just have the debt and even if
the debt burden is going down, they're
still burdened by all that debt.
Meanwhile, their wages are losing value,
right? Or if they have savings, that
savings is is losing value.
Um
wealthier people tend not to have wages,
you know, maybe they run a business and
they just can raise their prices.
Um and so the way a lot of wealthier
people earn their money, uh they have an
easier time,
you know, recouping the the increase in
the cost of living. But a lot of
workers,
uh you know, a lot of times wages don't
keep up with other prices.
And so even though your prices are going
up, your income is not going up
proportionate. Your income maybe prices
went up 100% but your income went up
70%, right? So, you're still behind. But
there are a lot of people that live on a
fixed income where they're getting
they're getting killed. The the middle
class and the poor suffer more as a
result of inflation.
>> Mhm. But if the rich
um
have the right mix of assets and
liabilities, yes, they can benefit from
inflation cuz inflation transfers wealth
from
uh
from uh debtor from creditors to
debtors. So, there are some rich people
who are going to suffer because of
inflation because they have a type of
portfolio that's going to be harmed,
right?
Uh Mhm. because inflation benefits
debtors and hurts creditors. And a lot
of rich people are creditors. If you
think about it, who is the biggest
debtor
in the world?
The US government, right? If you we're
probably the biggest debtor in the
universe, right? I mean, I don't I don't
know I mean if there's life on any other
planets, but I'm sure the US government
is more in debt than any government on
any planet in the universe. That'd be my
guess. So, the US government creates
inflation because it benefits the US
government to have inflation. Right.
>> and experts are pursuing the public that
inflation is good. This this is what
we've been taught since we were little
and I was thinking this like in ancient
Egypt there is slaves building pyramids,
ancient China slaves building the Great
Wall and modern world, it's the
financial monetary system that traps and
this is how a society should work. I was
reading this report that the bottom 50%
of the world owns 1% of the total asset,
which I think that is a
different way to say slavery or like or
or poverty.
>> Yeah, I mean, there is a a huge divide
now. I think the gap between the richest
and the poorest and I think that's been
exacerbated
uh by the monetary and fiscal policies.
I'm like, is this just how the world
should work?
That there has to be someone in the
bottom doing
>> it is bad. I think the the distribution
that we have now
is not as is it would be better if we
had
a a
not equitable but we had a a
distribution that wasn't skewed. Mhm.
And it wouldn't be. And your point that
you made about how the government keeps
trying to convince us that we need
inflation.
>> Right.
That was all government propaganda
because the government needs inflation.
Because that's how it diminishes its
debts. That's how it plays Santa Claus.
That's how it you know, it can give
people something for nothing. It creates
this something with inflation.
But the whole idea that inflation is
necessary to have a prosperous economy,
right? They what the what they say is
that well,
we have to make sure prices go up.
>> Yeah. Cuz they say if prices
went down, nobody would buy anything.
>> Exactly.
>> Which is
Because
people buy more when prices go down.
Mhm.
>> Because I mean,
you can afford it.
Right? If you can't afford to buy
something, let's say something, you
know, like the the first uh cell phone
that came out.
Uh I think, you know, the portable cell
phone maybe was three, four, five
thousand dollars, but that's when you
could buy a car for that amount of
money, right?
>> Wow. Only rich people used to buy cell
phones.
Why does everybody have a cell phone?
Because they're cheaper now, right? As
the prices went down, more and more
people were able to afford them.
According to the government, that should
not have happened, right? The price
needs to go up.
Yeah. It's so ridiculous or they'll say,
well,
you know, if you think the price of food
is going to go down, you you won't buy
it. You'll just wait. So, I'm going to
go hungry? It's like, oh, I'm really
hungry, but if I wait a month, the price
of that food is going to be a little bit
cheaper. So, I'm going to just starve
myself while I'm waiting for the price
of food. No, you're going to buy the
food when you need it. Mhm. But you hope
the price is lower in the future. I
mean, who who really thinks, yeah, I
really hope my grocery bill goes up. I
hope it costs me more to buy gas next
time I need it, right? Or I really hope
that the my tuition goes up for my kids
next year. You know, that this is
nonsense.
Everybody wants lower prices. Everybody
benefits from lower prices. It doesn't
it doesn't stop the man. Like that like,
oh, it people are going to buy things
when they need them.
They're not going to hold off
indefinitely for a lower price unless
they can't afford the current price.
Then they will hold off until they can
afford it. But the the they overlook the
the time value, right?
>> Right. There there is value
in owning something today. So, even if I
know, oh, if I buy a car today, it's X
amount of money.
If I wait a year, it'll be 1% or 2%
cheaper, right? Well, okay, but I need
the car right now. I can't wait a year.
My other car is broken down.
Even though I know it will be cheaper in
the future, I'm still going to buy one.
Right.
>> Because I need it now and that 2% is
more valuable. They're trying to justify
inflation or they'll say businesses
can't make a profit unless the prices
are going up.
And that's not true. In fact, cell phone
companies make a lot more money today
selling cell phones for cheap than they
did 30 years ago when they were a lot
more expensive because they have more
volume. And so what matters to business
is not the price but the margin.
And as long as margins are being
maintained,
even if prices are falling, I'll make
more money because I'll sell more goods.
And and so the all these stories that
the economists tell to try to justify
deliberately creating inflation are it's
all wrong. We don't need inflation. The
government has brainwashed people into
believing that that inflation is a good
thing because the government
benefits from it. The government steals
through inflation. Inflation is really
like a hidden tax and the last thing we
need is taxes. You know, we don't need
more taxes. I think the
the question I want to ask you before we
wrap up this conversation is you called
out the '08 financial crisis while
everybody was still partying.
Everybody's like the economy is great
and then um I watched a lot of the
interviews and
the hosts were shocked. They're like,
oh, you've been talking about this since
'06 or like a couple years ago and I
want to know what you saw then and are
we seeing the same thing now? Yeah, you
know, well, a lot of the problems that
the mainstream was overlooking
in the years leading up to the '08
financial crisis, they've been
overlooking very similar problems ever
since that crisis. That we're in a
bigger bubble in general now
than we were then as far as, you know,
the excess leverage and
uh the inflated prices, asset prices.
Um you know, I think the housing market
is probably in worse shape now
than it was before the mortgage crisis.
Uh I think real estate prices
are dramatically,
you know, overpriced in the US. Prices
should come down,
I don't know, maybe 30%, 40% uh
nationwide. But, that would, you know,
put most people underwater on their
mortgages and would would result in a
wave of defaults and foreclosures and
bankruptcies. I mean,
you know, and and there's a lot of other
debt, you know, a lot of other people
that own a long-term, low-yielding debt.
I mean, I think interest rates need to
go much higher. You know, they're being
they've been artificially suppressed.
So,
there's a there's a big big problem to
me that's even bigger than what was
going unnoticed
uh before '08. So, I think we're headed
for a a crisis that will be an order of
magnitude greater Mhm. than than '08.
But, to put things in perspective for,
like, crypto and where we are here at at
this event, there I see a lot of
similarities there as well as, you know,
I saw during the dot-com bubble and the
housing bubble, where you have people
that are trapped in a bubble and don't
realize that they are.
Right? They And and so, there's a lot of
uh
uh malinvestment.
Uh as a result, you have all these
companies, you know, like look at all
these companies in the exhibit hall
here. Uh most of these companies are
going to go bankrupt.
Uh but, they're attracting capital now
because people want to get in on the
action. They they they, you know, they
there's so much hype uh around crypto
and blockchain and everything related to
it. And there is a a a disaster coming
for this industry and for the people who
have invested in it.
>> are going to zero. Uh of course, I would
think,
you know, I I would want this industry
to go forward and all that, but you also
see a lot of really strange behaviors,
like any other industries.
Uh
but, it's always
so much fun talking to you.
Thank you so much.
>> talking to you. Please come back soon.
Sure.